<PAGE>
	<VAR match="VAR_ORIGIN" replace="" />
	<VAR match="VAR_CVSID" replace="$Id: source.xml,v 1.10 2005/08/01 13:47:03 dwmw2 Exp $"/>
	<INCLUDE file="inc/header.tmpl" />

	<VAR match="VAR_SEL_SOURCE" replace="selected" />
	<PARSE file="menu1.xml" />
	
	<INCLUDE file="inc/content.tmpl" />

<h2>GIT vs. Linux 3.x</h2>

    <P>MTD development is kept in GIT and managed according to standard Linux
    development practices. Development is based off of one of several trees,
    depending on what you're targeting. For MTD development, patches are kept
    in the <TT>linux-mtd.git</TT> and <TT>l2-mtd.git</TT> repositories. The
    former targets the current release cycle (use this only for bugfixes other
    material that's worthy of rapid integration into Linus' tree), while the
    latter targets the next Linux release (use this for most development).
    UBI and UBIFS development is tracked separately, in
    <TT>linux-ubifs.git</TT>. User-space tools are kept in
    <TT>mtd-utils.git</TT>.</P>

    <P>All of the kernel trees are included in the
    <a href="http://git.kernel.org/?p=linux/kernel/git/next/linux-next.git">linux-next</a>
    tree and are viewable using gitweb at <A
    HREF="http://git.infradead.org/">http://git.infradead.org/</A>, along
    with a separate tree for the userspace tools, and users' own trees.</P>

<table cellpadding="8">
    <tr>
        <th>Tree Name</th><th>GIT URL</th><th>Gitweb URL</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>
            MTD
        </td>
        <td>
            <tt>git://git.infradead.org/linux-mtd.git</tt>
        </td>
        <td>
            <a href="http://git.infradead.org/linux-mtd.git">
                http://git.infradead.org/linux-mtd.git</a>
        </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>
            MTD (next)
        </td>
        <td>
            <tt>git://git.infradead.org/l2-mtd.git</tt>
        </td>
        <td>
            <a href="http://git.infradead.org/l2-mtd.git">
                http://git.infradead.org/l2-mtd.git</a>
        </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>
            UBI / UBIFS
        </td>
        <td>
            <tt>git://git.infradead.org/linux-ubifs.git</tt>
        </td>
        <td>
            <a href="http://git.infradead.org/linux-ubifs.git">
                http://git.infradead.org/linux-ubifs.git</a>
        </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>
            MTD user-space tools
        </td>
        <td>
            <tt>git://git.infradead.org/mtd-utils.git</tt>
        </td>
        <td>
            <a href="http://git.infradead.org/mtd-utils.git">
                http://git.infradead.org/mtd-utils.git</a>
        </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
        <td>
            This website
        </td>
        <td>
            <tt>git://git.infradead.org/mtd-www.git</tt>
        </td>
        <td>
            <a href="http://git.infradead.org/mtd-www.git">
                http://git.infradead.org/mtd-www.git</a>
        </td>
    </tr>
</table>

    <P>Gitweb can give patches between specific points in the tree. To
    obtain the full patch between Linus' official kernel tree and the
    current MTD tree, use the following URL: <A
    HREF="http://git.infradead.org/?p=linux-mtd.git;a=commitdiff_plain;h=master;hp=linus">http://git.infradead.org/?p=linux-mtd.git;a=commitdiff_plain;h=master;hp=linus</A>. This
    produces a full patch from the branch known as '<TT>linus</TT>' in
    the git repository, which represents the last point at which
    Linus' official kernel tree was merged into the MTD git tree. This
    should apply correctly to the <em>current</em> kernel, but beware
    that it will not include changes which were already taken by
    Linus.</P>
    
    <P>When cloning the tree, please try to conserve network bandwidth (and
      your own disk space) by using 'alternates' -- if you have a local clone
      of Linus' official kernel tree, share the object directory with that
      instead of downloading the same objects all over again. With GIT 1.3.0
      and onwards, that's simple enough. Assuming you have a local tree named
      '<TT>~/git/linux</TT>' already, you can clone the MTD tree as follows:</P>
<p>
<tt>git clone --reference ~/git/linux git://git.infradead.org/linux-mtd.git</tt>
</p>

<p>Users with accounts on git.infradead.org can create their own trees
there, which are also accessible via public git:// URLs and visible in
gitweb. For more details see the <A HREF="doc/git.html">GIT HOWTO</A>.</p>


<hr size="2" />

<h2>Patch submission</h2>

<p>
If you have the facility to do so, please create a temporary git tree
from which patches can be pulled. The <A HREF="doc/git.html">GIT
HOWTO</A> documents how to do this. Please make sure that any such
such GIT trees are based on the current linux-mtd GIT tree and not on
Linus' tree, so that unnecessary merges are avoided.
</p>
<P>Users without an account on <TT>git.infradead.org</TT> (which is a
different machine to the old <tt>cvs.infradead.org</tt>) may send trivial patches
to the mailing list -- but expect to be given an account and expected to
use git if you make a habit of it.</P>

<p>If you are sending patches to the <a href="mail.html">mailing list</a>,
please remember to base them on the appropriate tree listed above, not Linus'
tree.</p>

<h3>Patch Format Guidelines</h3>
<p>
In order to make the lives of the patchmonkeys/maintainers easier, a few
simple rules should be followed when submitting patches</p>

<ol>
<li>Provide a short summary line of the patch in the format:</li><br />
<code>[PATCH] mtd: DETAILEDTARGET: short summary</code>
<p>
DETAILEDTARGET should be one of the MTD subcomponents, e.g. nand, chips,
maps, core, and/or a filename if it simplifies the review/recognition of
patch relevance.</p>

<li>Empty new line</li>
<li>Add a long comment to explain the patch</li>
<p>
Please use understandable wording.  We are not experts in witchcraft.  Please
omit comments which just resemble the short summary line for simple patches.</p>

<li>Add the appropriate origin information</li>
<code>
[From: Realname &amp;lt;realmail&amp;gt;]<br />
[Acked-by: Realname &amp;lt;realmail&amp;gt;]<br />
Signed-off-by: Realname &amp;lt;realmail&amp;gt;<br />
</code>
</ol>

<hr size="2" />

<h2><a name="kernelversions">Kernel versions</a></h2>
<p>The MTD code in the linux kernel is updated from the MTD GIT tree
in kernel version <b>3.x (newest) only</b>.  The 2.4 kernel does not
have NAND support in JFFS2, and will not have anything but
high-priority bug-fixes applied to it.</p>
<P>As of March 2005 we dropped Linux 2.4 support from CVS head. This
means we no longer care whether the CVS code can be used on Linux 2.4
or not.</P>
<P>As of April 2006 we stopped using CVS altogether and switched to a
  GIT tree based on the current 2.6 kernel. You may be able to massage
  the current code to work in older kernels, if you have a sufficient
  supply of illegal narcotics that you actually desire such a
  thing. Please don't ask us about it though.</P>

<P>If you are using the ancient 2.4 kernel, that's probably
because you're interested in stablity -- it is old and long-tested
code. If that's what you want, then you should use the original JFFS2
code which is part of the 2.4 kernel. It's old and slow and doesn't
support NAND flash, but it <em>is</em> stable, and is maintained.</P>
<p>The MTD community is neither able nor interested to provide support for new MTD and JFFS2 code with ancient kernels. 
Move yourself and update to a recent kernel. If you use a vendor supplied kernel, 
please  get support from your kernel vendor.  Do not ask on the mailinglist for help with 
 such problems. You are either ignored or you get a pointer to this text. 
Please save the bandwidth and our time to sort out such questions.</p>

	<INCLUDE file="inc/footer.tmpl" />
</PAGE>
